Guide to the Voices of Brooklyn oral histories 2008.031
Brooklyn Historical Society
Voices of Brooklyn oral histories
2008-
1998-
Brooklyn Historical Society
2008.031
86.01 Gigabytes in 334 files; Running time (of described records): 114 hours, 7 minutes, 26 seconds; in one records carton.
This collection includes oral histories collected through several projects undertaken by the Brooklyn Historical Society beginning in 2006. The assembled collection took shape in 2008 under the project title "Brooklyn History Makers." The ongoing oral history collection, retitled in 2016, features a broad range of narrators: jazz musicians, business leaders, civil rights activists, authors, artists, sports players, and longtime neighborhood residents who describe the changes they have observed in their neighborhoods over decades.
Arrangement
The oral history interview collection is organized into eight series based on content. Series 1: Arts and entertainment consists of recordings that focus on the narrator's production of works of art or entertainment media. Photographers, authors, and musicians are prominent.
Series 2: Business and industry includes interviews thematically linked by owning or operating workplaces. Store managers, small business owners, and restaurateurs are mainstays.
Oral histories represented in Series 3: Civic leaders pertain to narrators speaking to their outsized contribution to how New York City citizens live, work, and conduct business in the five boroughs. Developers, government officials, executives, benefactors, and board members are included.
Series 4: Community activists consists of the gathered recordings of people who have a history of or were presently supporting an underrepresented segment of society, or forming a social movement, which thereby effected broad change to a neighborhood, much of Brooklyn, or the country. The content relates directly to organized support of those harmed in natural disasters, creating cooperative business models, forming architectural preservation groups, and documenting civil rights and social justice movements.
Series 5: Our neighbors is the largest series of the collection and is likely to remain so. The interviews include people from diverse backgrounds making observations or sharing recollections about the growth and condition of several neighborhoods within Brooklyn. Brooklyn Heights, Carroll Gardens, and Fort Greene were heavily represented as of 2017.
Oral histories within Series 6: Sports and leisure pertain to narrators who proactively contributed to the athletic pursuits or relaxing diversions of Brooklyn. Professional and amateur athletes and Coney Island novelties are included.
Series 7: Veterans and wartime consists of the gathered recordings of those focusing on their time serving or time served within the country's armed forces, as well as those in support service organizations. There is also some recollection of civilian life before, during, and after mobilizations for fighting abroad. World War II, Vietnam, and the War on Terror are prominent.
Series 8: Waterfront series consists of six oral history interviews that were conducted during 2017 as a part of the research process for Brooklyn Historical Society's Waterfront exhibition. The interviews are arranged alphabetically by narrator's last name.
The Voices of Brooklyn oral histories are a combination of project-based and individual interviews assembled by oral historians and Library and Archives management of Brooklyn Historical Society. Series were formed with a basis on content in a collection audit phase by the oral history project archivist. The oral history recordings are arranged alphabetically within each series. Two interviews are accompanied by transcripts in electronic files: Shelby White in Series 3 and Albert King in Series 6.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers with varied restrictions according to narrator agreement. Oral histories can be accessed onsite at the Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library and online on the Oral History Portal. Administrative materials are open to researchers upon request and are accessible onsite at the Othmer Library.
Historical note
Oral histories were conducted for projects with a focus on a Brooklyn neighborhood, such as Park Slope, Fort Greene, Coney Island, Red Hook and Vinegar Hill, as well as for projects tied thematically to the Brooklyn Dodgers, Miss Rheingold, and sports. Other individual interviews were arranged for "Brooklyn History Makers" consideration and others were not formally assigned to any project, listing, or collection when they were conducted. Staff for this project included Sady Sullivan (Director of Oral History), Corie Trancho Robie (Interviewer), Alexis Taines Coe (Interviewer), Manissa McCleave Maharawal (Interviewer) and other interviewers. Nearly all recordings and transcripts were born-digital.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The oral histories that make up this collection were conducted by a team at Brooklyn Historical Society including an oral historian and graduate student assistants. The bulk of this work commenced in 2006 and continues at present.
Scope and Contents
The Voices of Brooklyn oral histories feature a broad range of narrators. Some are well-known public figures and others are well-known in their communities. This ongoing collection focuses on Brooklyn history and the experiences of these narrators document national and international history as well. The oldest narrator in this collection was born in 1910. Within the collection are several series.
Oral History note
Oral history interviews are intimate conversations between two people, both of whom have generously agreed to share these recordings with the Brooklyn Historical Society archives and with researchers. Please listen in the spirit with which these were shared. Researchers will understand that:
1. The Brooklyn Historical Society abides by the General Principles & Best Practices for Oral History as agreed upon by the Oral History Association (2009) and expects that use of this material will be done with respect for these professional ethics.
2. Every oral history relies on the memories, views and opinions of the narrator. Because of the personal nature of oral history, listeners may find some viewpoints or language of the recorded participants to be objectionable. In keeping with its mission of preservation and unfettered access whenever possible, BHS presents these views as recorded.
3. Transcripts commissioned by a party other than BHS serve as a guide to the interview and are not considered verbatim. The audio recording should be considered the primary source for each interview. It may contain natural false starts, verbal stumbles, misspeaks, repetitions that are common in conversation, and other passages and phrases omitted from the transcript. This decision was made because BHS gives primacy to the audible voice and also because some researchers do find useful information in these verbal patterns.
4. Unless these verbal patterns are germane to your scholarly work, when quoting from this material researchers are encouraged to correct the grammar and make other modifications maintaining the flavor of the narrator's speech while editing the material for the standards of print.
Separated Materials
Documents relating to the accessioning, exhibiting, and administrative processes are separate from the collection and are in the administrative files at Brooklyn Historical Society.
Related Materials
Brooklyn Historical Society has oral history collections and other records related to the Voices of Brooklyn oral histories.
• Narrator Randy Weston recorded an oral history for the Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation oral histories (2008.030).
• Narrator Ronald Shiffman recorded an oral history for the Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation oral histories (2008.030). He donated his papers to BHS in 2013 (2013.023).
• Narrator Carlos E. Russell recorded an oral history for the Hispanic Communities Documentation Project records and oral histories (1989.004).
• Narrator Lucille Fornasieri Gold donated her photographs to BHS in 2008 (2008.013).
• Narrator Ellen Liman made a gift to BHS containing her collection of nineteenth century McLoughlin Brothers children books (2007.002).
• Narrator Frank Palescandolo made a gift to BHS containing photographs and a postcard of Villa Joe's in Coney Island in 1992. (V1992.014) His manuscript collection is also at BHS. (2011.014)
• Narrator Robert MacCrate made a gift to BHS containing the papers of Kenneth M. Swezey (2007.005).
• Narrator Shelby White is the subject of a photograph and an interview on audiocassette in two folders of the Packer Collegiate Institute records (2014.019).
• Narrator DK Holland's work on the community newsletter The Hill is represented in Box 1 of Brooklyn neighborhood associations and civic organizations publications (ARC.167).
• Narrator Ed Moran focused on the history of the Lafayette Avenue Presbyterian Church in his oral history recordings. The church's records were donated in 2009 and 2015 (2009.011).
• Narrator Alan Nisselson donated the Nisselson family papers to BHS in 2016 (2016.022).
• Narrator Mary DeSaussure Sobers donated her collection to BHS in 2005 (2005.053).
For more information on these collections please visit our online finding aid portal.
Related collections located elsewhere include:
• Narrator Maxine Wolfe's oral history in the ACT UP Oral History Project videotapes (MssCol 6148) at the New York Public Library and as a transcript on the ACT UP Oral History Project website, http://www.actuporalhistory.org/interviews/index.html
• The James E. Jackson and Esther Cooper Jackson Papers at the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive (TAM.347)
• The Lesbian Herstory Archives in Park Slope, Brooklyn, and http://www.lesbianherstoryarchives.org/
Interviews (sound recordings); Oral histories (document genres); Transcripts; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Genealogy; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Religious life and customs; New York (N.Y.); New York (State) |x Politics and government; Activism; Amusement parks |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Art |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Arts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Business enterprises |z New York (State) |z Kings County; City churches |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Civic improvement |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Civic leaders |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community activists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Community development |z New York (State) |z New York; Community identity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z New York; Family life |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Musicians |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Neighborhoods -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Outdoor recreation; Performing arts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Social justice |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Sports |z United States |y 20th century; Storefronts--New York (State)--Kings County; Veterans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Vietnam War, 1961-1975; World War, 1939-1945 |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn Dodgers (Baseball team)
- Voices of Brooklyn oral histories: Arts and entertainment, 2006-; 2008.031.1
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes oral histories collected through several projects undertaken by Brooklyn Historical Society beginning in 2006. The assembled series took shape in 2008 under the project title "Brooklyn History Makers." The ongoing oral history series, retitled in 2016, features a range of narrators: jazz musicians, photographers, authors, and artists among them, who describe the changes they have observed in their neighborhoods over decades.
  - Engberg, Marianne, 2009 December 10; 2008.031.1.001
    Biographical / Historical
    Marianne Engberg is a Danish transplant who moved to the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood in 1968 with her husband, a furniture designer, and young son. An artist, Engberg is a professional photographer who spent her early career traveling around the world shooting for magazines before starting her own commercial studio in Manhattan. Her family moved to the Fort Greene neighborhood in 1972 and they renovated their brownstone, where she still lived as of 2017.
    In this interview, Marianne Engberg talks about moving to Brooklyn as a young family in the 1970s and how their early part of her and her husband's careers were focused on trying to establish themselves in New York City. She describes how the couple fell in love with Brooklyn, their movement from the neighborhood of Brooklyn Heights to the Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn, and the differences, trials, and joys of living in Fort Greene for over thirty years. She reflects on the role race has played in her neighborhood, how the neighborhood has changed in the past decade, and what gentrification has done to their area. Interview conducted by Alexis Taines Coe.
    Conditions Governing Access and Use
    Access is available onsite at Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library and the Oral History Portal. Use of oral histories other than for private study, scholarship, or research requires permission from BHS by contacting library@brooklynhistory.org.
    Architecture |x Conservation and restoration; Artists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Arts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn Heights (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Brownstone buildings |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Fort Greene Park (New York, N.Y.); Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Historic districts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Neighborhood government |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Neighborhoods -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Photographers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Washington Park (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Academy of Music; Brooklyn Technical High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Engberg, Jan, -2006; Engberg, Marianne, 1937-; New York Naval Shipyard
  - Forbes, Sally, 2013 March 19; 2008.031.1.002
    Access to this recording is restricted by the donor. Please contact library@brooklynhistory.org for further questions.
  - George, Nelson, 2009 November 20; 2008.031.1.003
    Born in 1957 and raised in the Brownsville and East New York neighborhoods of Brooklyn, Nelson George moved to the Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn in the mid-1980s. Best known as an author and filmmaker, his non-fiction books have largely focused on histories of popular music and biographies of Black musicians. He helped bankroll Spike Lee's filming of She's Gotta Have It (1986) and has produced, written and directed for the screen ever since. He featured Brooklyn in his book City Kid: A Writer's Memoir of Ghetto Life and Post-Soul Success and the documentary Brooklyn Boheme. In 2016, he was a writer on Netflix's The Get-Down and he was continuing work on a series of detective novels. George shares credits and creative content at his website https://nelson-george.squarespace.com/.
    In the interview, Nelson George takes in the Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn from several perspectives. Moving in a mostly chronological approach, he recalls trips with his mother to the Abraham & Straus department store on Fulton Street and visits as an independent young adult to a girlfriend in the neighborhood. George remembers the floor plan of his first Fort Greene apartment in the 1980s, and a theft that took place just outside his window. He reflects on the culturally vibrant time of African American artists inhabiting the area and how their departure opened a void that was filled by a new upper-middle class and young professionals starting families. George's friends Spike Lee, Chris Rock, and Vernon Reid all figure into his personal connections with the neighborhood. In much of the final half-hour, he gives his points of view on several Fort Greene landmarks and shares how affected he was as a young writer by living in the same Fort Greene where Richard Wright once wrote. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
    African American neighborhoods -- New York (State) -- Kings County; African Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community identity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Fort Greene Park (New York, N.Y.); Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Musicians |z New York (State) |z New York; Performing arts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race identity; Brooklyn Academy of Music
  - Liman, Ellen, 2007 September 4; 2008.031.1.006
  - Newman, Anne, 2009 July 8; 2008.031.1.007
    Born in 1932, Anne Newman grew up in Chino, California. The daughter of a father who became Chino's mayor, she attended Chino High School and went on to major in political science at Pomona College and University of California, Los Angeles. While a graduate student in social work at University of Southern California, she appeared in a student film and was drawn to acting. In 1959, Newman entered a Miss Rheingold contest as the Brooklyn-based brewery was cracking the California market. As a semi-finalist, she was flown to New York City and booked at the Waldorf-Astoria Hotel. She was interviewed there, chosen as a finalist, and received a prize of $25,000. For weeks in the summer of 1959, finalists campaigned to be Miss Rheingold of 1959-1960. Newman met her first husband, Harper's Bazaar publisher Robert MacLeod, when he was judging the contest. Although not chosen as Miss Rheingold, she joined the Ford Models agency and took acting classes. The couple relocated to Malibu, California in the mid-1960s and had a son. She later divorced and married actor Paul Mantee. While acting, she was repeatedly cast by one agency for commercial work. Her third husband, Joe Bacal, cofounded that agency. When she moved back to New York, Newman worked in children's television production in the mid-1980s and then volunteered with Bread and Roses, a cultural project of the 1199 Service Employees International Union. Leading up to this 2009 interview, Newman had chaired a women's theater group and was staying politically active with EMILY's List. She reunited with several Miss Rheingold finalists in 2012 at New-York Historical Society's exhibition on local breweries, and this inspired her 2015 documentary Beauty and the Beer: 1940-1963.
    In this interview, Anne Newman speaks about much of her early adult life as a graduate student seeking acting roles and her lucky break at becoming a finalist in a Miss Rheingold contest in 1959. She also recalls pivotal moments like meeting her first husband, modeling, becoming a mother, getting into television production on The Great Space Coaster show, marrying her best friend and third husband, and volunteering. Newman considers the unique social significance of the beauty contest in the late 1950s, contrasts that with political campaigns and reality shows circa 2008, and reflects on her early recognition of her feminism and how that empowered her choices through much of her life. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
    Activism; Actors -- United States; Advertisements; Beauty contests; Beer; Breweries |z New York (State) |z Kings County; California; Feminism |z New York (State) |z New York; Models (Persons); New York (N.Y.) |x Social life and customs |y 20th century; Performing arts |z New York (State) |z New York; Politics and culture |z United States; Women |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social conditions; Women |z United States |x Social conditions; Ford Models, Inc.; Miss Rheingold Pageant; Newman, Anne, 1932-; Rheingold Breweries, Inc.
  - Palescandolo, Frank, 2009 February 10; 2008.031.1.008
    Frank Palescandolo was born on the Lower East Side of Manhattan in 1917, and moved to the Coney Island neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1919. He grew up there and lived above the restaurant (Villa Joe's) owned and run by his family. His parents, both immigrants from Italy, ran the restaurant; it seated 500 people and was one of the biggest in Brooklyn. As a boy, he and his family had some local celebrity and were good friends with prominent members of the area, such as the Tilyou family, who ran and owned Steeplechase Park. Palescandolo was a trained social worker, and spent the majority of his time working with youths and longshoremen in the Red Hook neighborhood of Brooklyn. He took over the family business when his father died and ran the restaurant in Coney Island until 1975, when it was sold to Urban Renewal. Under the pseudonym Frank Paley, he completed Rumble on the Docks, his first book, in 1953, and spent his life writing twenty-six books that range from novels to histories to translations. Palescandolo classifies himself as one of the few authentic Brooklyn writers.
    In the interview, Frank Palescandolo talks of the Coney Island neighborhood of Brooklyn's past; restaurants that used to be there, the different ethnicities of the people that visited the beach, and the amusement parks that the area is famous for: Luna Park, Steeplechase Park, and Dreamland. He reflects on the restaurant his family had at Coney Island while he was growing up, Villa Joe's, and remembers his early days in the area; talking about his parents' lives as younger people, the house and restaurant they built, and the small farms that neighbors kept on vacant neighborhood lots. He laments the closing of the restaurant in 1975 and the way in which Coney Island has suffered in recent years. He discusses the Red Hook neighborhood of Brooklyn in the 1950s; the teenage gangs there, the crime that was rampant in the area, and how he came to know many of the men involved in that underworld through his social work. He discusses his novel Rumble on the Docks, which takes place in Red Hook and deals with gangs and the gang violence endemic to the neighborhood in the late twentieth century. He recounts how he started writing because he was stuck in bed with the flu, and how he spent roughly thirty years prior to this 2009 interview as a writer. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
    Amusement parks |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x History; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Economic conditions |y 20th century; Coney Island (New York, N.Y.); Crime -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Gangs |z New York (State) |z Kings Country; Great Depression |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Italian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Red Hook (New York, N.Y.); Restaurateurs -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Restaurants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Urban renewal |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Waterfronts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Luna Park (New York, N.Y.); Palescandolo, Frank J.; Steeplechase Park (New York, N.Y.); Villa Joe's (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
  - Redbone, Martha, 2011; 2008.031.1.009
    Redbone, Martha
  - Weiner, Gina Ingoglia, 2014 April 21; 2008.031.1.011